Animation Number 1
I see.. Then you don't see the white snake anymore?
（電話:阿良々木(あららぎ)）
へえ
じゃあ
もう見えなくなったんだな？
その白い蛇ってヤツは
Y-Yeah. I'm fine now.
（千石(せんごく)）
う… うん　もう大丈夫なの
Hmm... If you were wrong in assuming it was just your imagination,
（電話:阿良々木）
ふ〜ん
もしも
気のせいってのが気のせいで
and it actually was an aberration, be sure to give me a call.
やっぱりそれが
何かの怪異だったりしたら
ちゃんと連絡しろよ
Y-Yeah, okay.
（千石）う… うん　分かった
Th-Thank you, Koyomi-oniichan.
あ… あ… あり…
ありがとう
To be honest I'd love to stay on the phone longer...
Animation Number 5
暦(こよみ)おにいちゃん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
ハア…
Looks like you lied to your dear Koyomi-oniichan. Is that okay?
愛しの暦おにいちゃんに
ウソをついちまったな
いいのかよ
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
D-Don't raise your voice so much.
あ… あんまり大きな声を
出さないで
You don't have to sneak around or anything. You're the only one that can hear my voice, Nadeko-chan.
（クチナワ）
別にコソコソしなくていいんだぜ
俺様の声が聞こえるのは
撫子(なでこ)ちゃんだけなんだから
I'm well aware.
Animation Number 12
If you can be so small, why did you first appear so big that you could wrap yourself around that shrine?
そんなに小さくなれるのなら
どうして 最初
あんな神社を全て巻き込むような
大きさで登場したの？
It was stage direction! I was just directing my own entrance.
演出だよ 演出
登場シーンの演出
Aberrations lose the meaning of their existence if humans aren't surprised by them.
怪異ってやつは
人間に驚いてもらわないことには
存在意義をなくしちまうからな
（千石）クチナワさん
Kuchinawa-san...
Are you someone—Are you the snake revered at that shrine?
あなたって
あの神社で祭られている人—
蛇なの？
Snake
Exactly. Well, not completely. That shrine's been forsaken for a while now.
（クチナワ）
そのとおり… とは言えねえな
あの神社は信仰を失って久しい
All it is now is a drift, filled with bad things. No, I think I'd be more correct saying it's a pile of rubbish.
今や ただの
よくないものの吹きだまりだ
いや 掃きだめといったほうが
正確かもしれねえ
Well...
Dear God...
Animation Number 19
（千石）
えっと
Then what do you want me to do, Kuchinawa-san?
それじゃあ
クチナワさん
How can I make up...
Animation Number 19
撫子は
何をしたらいいの？
I mean, what would you like of me?
Animation Number 19
What I would like to ask of you, Nadeko-chan, is to find something.
（クチナワ）
俺様が撫子ちゃんに
お願いしたいことは
探しものだ
Nadeko-chan, I want you to find my corpse.
撫子ちゃんには
Strangely... No.
Animation Number 22
俺様の死体を
探してほしい
Oddly.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Nadeko Medusa         Part Two
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Animation Number 24
1st  of  November
Stop
The next morning I headed to school like always.
（千石）
翌朝 撫子は
いつもどおり学校に向かいます
Yes. No matter how many hallucinations I see, I must go to school.
ええ　いくら幻覚を見ようと
学校には
行かなくてはならないのです
That's being a junior high student.
それが中学生です
I get up in the morning, change into my uniform, and head out.
朝起きて 制服に着替え 通学路に
The usual way to school
Animation Number 28
A stunning display of junior high school life.
見事な中学生ライフ
There's one thing different from usual: the white scrunchie wrapped around my right wrist.
唯一 いつもと違うところといえば
右手首に巻かれた
白いシュシュです
I'm lucky that
Animation Number 34
Y-You know, Kuchinawa-san
（千石）
ね… ねえ クチナワさん
it pretty well
Animation Number 34
fits my
usual style.
Animation Number 34
can't you make it so no one else can see you?
撫子以外の人には
見えないようになれないの？
It's not impossible, but I don't want to use any more power than I am already.
（クチナワ）なれないこともねえが
これ以上
余計な力は使いたくないんでな
Rest assured. They can't hear me.
安心しな
声は聞こえねえんだし
And while we're at school, I'll pretend I'm just an accessory. I won't infringe on your everyday life.
学校では ちゃんと
ただのアクセサリーのふりを
しといてやるからよ
Thus I arrived at the school.
Animation Number 36
Hey! Hey, Nadeko!
Animation Number 38
Why do you change shoes? Why is there a need to do such a thing?
どうして靴を履き替えるんだ？
どうして
そんなことをする必要がある？
I don't know. Why is it? I've never thought of it before.
さあ なんでかな
考えたことなかったけど
Probably to keep the school building clean.
校舎内を汚さないようにだよ
Animation Number 42
Um, don't talk at all, okay?
あの…
しゃべらないでね
Yeah, I know that. You don't need to double-check with me.
（クチナワ）ああ 分かってるさ
念を押す必要なんかねえって
I'm a pretty quiet guy in the first place. Just like you, Nadeko-chan.
そもそも俺様は無口なんだから
撫子ちゃんと同じくな
Nanahyakuichi Public Middle School / Classroom
Animation Number 44
School, huh? There was a similar type of educational activity going on at the shrine in its day.
（クチナワ）
学校ね
まあ あの神社でも
昔は似たような教育活動は
行われていたんだがな
It's unnaturally orderly. Gives me the creeps...
不自然に秩序立って気持ち悪いぜ
No, is this something unique about this particular class?
いや これは
このクラス独特のものなのかな
Everyone seems to be keeping each other in check, and they're all uptight or something.
なんか 互いにけん制し合って
ピリピリしてるっつうか
なんつうか
I left the classroom. I crossed the corridor and climbed the stairs.
Animation Number 53
You know, Kuchinawa-san...
ねえ クチナワさん
I went all the way to the "off limits" door to the roof on the top floor.
Animation Number 53
What is it?
（クチナワ）何だよ
Shut up.
黙って
I'm a calm, shy, quiet girl.
撫子はね
おとなしくて内気で物静かな子なの
Like someone who is unnoticeable?
（クチナワ）
どこにいるんだか
分かんねえようなヤツだな
（千石）そう
Right. Someone who is unnoticeable.
どこにいるんだか
分かんないような子
I start talking to my wrist.
Animation Number 56
That's what I am.
それが撫子なの
It's me.
Animation Number 56
If you saw such a person, who is unnoticeable, talking to her wrist,
そういう どこにいるんだか
分からないような子が
自分の手首と
お話しているのを見たら
クラスメートのみんなは
どう思うと思う？
what do you think their classmates would think?
What would they think?
（クチナワ）どう思うんだよ
They'd all think, "How pitiful."
かわいそうな子って思うの
You think so? I don't think much will change at all.
（クチナワ）そうか？
大して何も変わらないって
気がするぜ
What changes if your position in the class moves a bit?
お前のポジションが
多少変わったところで
何が変わるんだよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I-In any case, Kuchinawa-san...
（千石）
と… とにかく クチナワさん
Come now, have you just been making your way through life with transitions like "in any case" and "that aside"?
おいおい 撫子ちゃん
お前は そうやって
"in any case"
Animation Number 64
〝とにかく〞とか
〝さておき〞とか
"that aside"
Animation Number 64
そういう切り替えの文言だけで
世渡りをしてきたのかい？
Without conversations?
ろくに会話もせず？
It's not that you're convinced of what I say, but you're not refuting it either.
俺様の言うことに
納得してるわけでもねえのに
反論するでもなく
検討もせずに棚上げにするってのが
So, pigeonholing it without consideration is the secret to your success?
撫子ちゃんの処世術かい？
In any case...
（千石）とにかく
My survival technique.
Animation Number 68
It is
looking away and staying quiet.
Animation Number 68
Waiting for the other
to just disappear.
Animation Number 68
You promised me that I could do whatever I wanted during the day...
昼間は撫子の自由に
していいって
約束… だよ？
It's not like your hands are chained.
Animation Number 69
That it was okay to only look for your corpse at night...
クチナワさんの死体を探すのは
夜だけでいいって
"Promise"
Animation Number 72
Looking for your corpse? Wh-What do you mean?
死体探し？
ど… どういうこと？
K-Kuchinawa-san's... corpse?
ク… クチナワさんの死体って？
In other words, my vessel.
My corpse used to revered at that shrine,
（クチナワ）
いわゆるご神体ってことだ
あの神社で かつて祭られていた
俺様の死体
That place
Animation Number 73
but it's now lost.
今は
失われちまったけどな
is just like any other now.
Animation Number 73
It's a sort of miracle I can be like this right now.
俺様がこうして こうあれることは
ひとつの奇跡だぜ
No, I have to say it's thanks to that vampire,
いや あの吸血鬼 忍野忍(おしのしのぶ)
I was drawn out by the queen of aberrations, Shinobu.
Animation Number 76
Oshino Shinobu, formerly Kiss-Shot Acerola-Orion Heart-Under-Blade
Something... undesirable.
Animation Number 76
旧キスショット･
アセロラ･オリオン—
The spell and its release were both amplified.
Animation Number 76
ハートアンダー･
ブレードの
And also revived the Serpent.
Animation Number 76
おかげというべきか
（千石）ハア…
The "bad things" gathering at the shrine thanks to her
（クチナワ）
あいつのせいで
あの神社に集まったよくないものが
今の俺様を形づくっている
エネルギー源なわけだが
are the source of energy supporting my current form.
But those same spiritual energies were also used for something completely trivial.
しかし その霊的エネルギーを
かなりどうでもいいことに
使われちまったんだ
いや まあ
It was Shinobu. It was Shinobu.
Animation Number 80
Well, that's thanks to Shinobu-chan as well.
She's both the cause and the effect.
Animation Number 80
それも
忍ちゃんなんだけどな
She just makes messes to get the credit for cleaning them up.
Animation Number 80
They were the "bad things" the vampire gathered into that energy drift as a result of her powers,
（クチナワ）
あの吸血鬼が自身の力の結果として
吹きだまりに集めた
よくないものなんだから
so it's up to her how she uses them up.
それを あいつがどうしようと
勝手なんだがな
しかし そのせいで
俺様という概念が
But because of that, it's true that the concept of my existence is on a thin rope now.
風前の灯火(ともしび)に
なっちまったことも確かだ
I understand.
（千石）分かった
In any case...
"In any case..."
Animation Number 64
とにかく
In any case, I need to find your corpse now, right, Kuchinawa-san?
とにかく 撫子は
クチナワさんの神体を
これから
探せばいいんだね
Just to stay in existence.
Animation Number 87
Just to stay possible.
If I find that vessel, you'll release me, right?
その神体を見つけたら
撫子を解放してくれるんだね？
Release you?
（クチナワ）解放って
I don't think I'm forcing you to do this, Nadeko-chan.
別に俺様は撫子ちゃんに
無理強いしているつもりは
ねえんだけどな
I'm just playing up on your sense of guilt.
あくまでも撫子ちゃんの罪悪感に
つけ込んでいるだけでな
I-In any case, I get it. I'll look for your vessel and find it.
（千石）
と… とにかく 分かったよ
撫子はクチナワさんの神体を探して
見つけるよ
That will be helpful. Though I won't thank you for it.
（クチナワ）
助かるぜ　礼は言わないがな
Why not?
Animation Number 93
Because you're a god?
Animation Number 94
So Kuchinawa-san, where is your corpse?
（千石）
それで クチナワさん
クチナワさんの死体は
どこにあるの？
No idea.
Animation Number 94
Is it somewhere on that mountain?
あの山のどこかにあるの？
No idea.
Animation Number 95
When did it disappear?
いつ なくなったの？
No idea.
Animation Number 96
How big is it?
どれくらいの大きさ？
No idea.
Animation Number 97
How old is it?
どれくらい古いの？
No idea.
Animation Number 98
Yeah! With that much information, it's as good as found!
それだけ情報があれば
もう見つけたも同然だね
って なんでやねん！
Now wait a minute!
That's impossible! I can try this for all my life, but it's still impossible.
無理だよ そんなの
一生かかっても無理だよ
Even if I reincarnate as a princess...
生まれ変わってお姫様になっても
無理だよ
What makes you think you'll reincarnate as a princess?
（クチナワ）
なんで生まれ変わったら
お姫様になることが前提なんだよ
No, no, don't worry.
Just match the "channel."
Animation Number 107
いやいや 心配するな
Since you've assimilated with me, I'm sure you can find it quickly.
俺様と同化している撫子ちゃんなら
すぐに見つけられるはずだぜ
Quickly...
すぐに？
If you do your best, quickly.
（クチナワ）頑張れば すぐにな
But I don't want to give it my best...
頑張りたくないな
No, that's where you're supposed to do your best.
（クチナワ）いや そこは頑張れよ
Effort or endure
Animation Number 112
I'll help you look for it...
探すのには協力するよ
said Nadeko.
Animation Number 113
But, Kuchinawa-san, I can go to school, right?
でも クチナワさん
学校には行ってもいいよね？
Huh?
Serpent / speaking
Animation Number 114
（クチナワ）
ああん？
Or rather, I'm asking if I can do everyday things normally...
というか
日常生活は
普通に送ってもいいよねってこと
B-Because I don't want
そ… その 撫子…
t-to raise suspicion.
あ… 怪しまれたくないの
Raise suspicion? Whose?
（クチナワ）怪しまれる？　誰に
To the Serpent's question,
Animation Number 119
Koyomi-oniichan.
（千石）
暦おにいちゃん
I answered honestly.
Animation Number 119
Because I said it was nothing. Because I said it was my imagination.
何もなかったってことに
したんだから
気のせいってことにしたんだから
If you're going to say that, Nadeko-chan,
それを言うなら 撫子ちゃん
rather than raising suspicion, isn't it that you don't want to make him worry?
怪しまれたくないじゃなくて
心配をかけたくないじゃねえのか？
だから 暦おにいちゃんに
That's why you told a lie like that to Koyomi-oniichan.
あんなウソを
ついたんじゃねえのかよ
Th-That's...
そ… それは…
You said you wanted him to save you,
（クチナワ）
助けてほしいとか言ってたくせに
あんなウソをついたのは
but I thought telling that kind of lie was because you didn't want him to worry about you. Was I wrong?
心配をかけたくなかったからだと
俺様は思っていたが
I failed. A gaffe.
Animation Number 126
違うのかい？
Th-That's not wrong...
ち… 違わないよ
Yeah, that's right. I don't want him to worry about me.
うん そうだよ
心配をかけたくないの
To worry...
心配を
"It's no big deal."
Animation Number 129
Well, whatever.
Then, let's say that's that.
（クチナワ）
じゃあ そういうことにしよう
Daytime is your time, and nighttime is my time.
昼間は撫子ちゃんの時間
夜間は俺様の時間
I will show gratitude to your self-sacrifice by swearing that I won't invade into your private times.
俺様は撫子ちゃんの献身に
感謝の意を示し
撫子ちゃんのプライベートタイムは
侵さないと誓う
Nanahyakuichi Public Middle School
Animation Number 133
The top of the stairs leading to the roof of the school
Liar. And you're a deity too!
（千石）
ウソつき
神様のくせに
All right, I get it. I just have to stay quiet, right?
（クチナワ）
分かった 分かった
黙ってればいいんだな
Sasayabu-sensei
Animation Number 134
Hey, Sengoku.
（笹薮(ささやぶ)）
お〜い 千石
nicknamed Panda-sensei
Animation Number 134
What are you doing there?
（笹薮）
お前
そんな所で何をしているんだ？
Uh, um, anything goes.
（千石）
な… な… 何でもありです！
I bit my tongue.
Animation Number 139
I mean, nothing.
何でもないです
（笹薮）ハア…
Class is about to start.
もうすぐ予鈴だぞ
All right.
分かりました
Sasayabu-sensei's words
Animation Number 146
By the way, Sengoku...
Sasayabu-sensei's words
Animation Number 146
（笹薮）
ところで 千石
Sasayabu-sensei's words
Animation Number 146
What happened with that thing I asked you to do?
先生が前に頼んでおいたことは
どうなった？
Wh-What happened?
ど… どうって…
Has it come any closer to being resolved?
（笹薮）
少しは解決に近づいたのか？
Um...
（千石）えっと…
Come on, I'm counting on you.
（笹薮）おいおい 頼むよ
You realize, like I do, that the problem needs to be resolved quickly, right?
早くあの問題を
解決しなきゃいけないことは
お前だって分かるだろ
You're my only hope, Class Prez Sengoku.
（笹薮）
お前だけが頼りなんだからな
The best student in the class
Animation Number 153
千石委員長
The student who manages all class affairs
Animation Number 153
You're class prez, Nadeko-chan?
（クチナワ）
撫子ちゃんって委員長だったのか？
Yeah, I'm class prez.
（千石）うん　委員長なんだ 撫子
（クチナワ）
ウソだ〜 委員長ってあれだろ？
You're kidding. Class prez is short for class president, right?
学級委員長のことだろ？
In other words, the most distinguished student that manages over the class, right?
つまりクラスを取りしきる—
クラスでいちばん偉い生徒って
ことだろ？
And that's you, Nadeko-chan? Huh?
それが
撫子ちゃんだって？
ああん？
Serpent / speaking
Animation Number 114
You realized as well that the class has a strange feel to it, right Kuchinawa-san?
（千石）
クラスが
変な雰囲気になっているのは
クチナワさんも分かったんでしょ？
So when the second term started, no one volunteered or nominated anyone as a candidate.
だから ２学期が始まるとき
立候補も推薦もなかったんだよね
And so, Nadeko was chosen.
それで撫子が選ばれたの
You got the short end of the stick.
Animation Number 161
Such a masochistic expression.
Under what circumstances does something like that happen?
（クチナワ）
どういう経緯を経たら
そういうことになるんだよ
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
If I were to force myself to answer...
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
（千石）
強いて言うなら
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
I'm not good at expressing myself.
I'm even worse at explaining things.
Animation Number 163
But still... uh...
I think it was because I was the only girl in the class that didn't get her hands on a "magic charm."
クラスの中で
おまじないに手を出していない
女子生徒が
撫子しかいなかったから…
かな？
Ah, so it was merely a process of elimination.
（クチナワ）
へえ つまりは消去法か
You could say that, I guess.
Animation Number 165
Basically, work no one wanted to do, or force someone else to do, was all forced on you, Nadeko-chan.
要するに 誰もやりたくないし
誰にもやらせたくない仕事を
撫子ちゃんに
押しつけたというわけか
ろくでもねえ連中だな
What a group of good-for-nothings, huh?
Serpent / speaking
Animation Number 114
ああん？
I don't think it's quite something that they forced on me, but...
（千石）
別に
押しつけられたって
わけじゃないんだけれど
For now, we'll say "that's that."
（クチナワ）
しかし それはそれとして
What was that teacher talking about earlier? What is it that he asked you to do?
さっき あの先生様が
おっしゃっていたのは何なんだ？
前に頼んでおいたことって何だよ
It doesn't involve you, Kuchinawa-san.
（千石）
関係ないでしょ
クチナワさんには
I said the line I prepared for this scenario just according to the book.
Animation Number 173
It doesn't involve me? And here I thought you and I were partners: one and the same.
（クチナワ）関係ないか？
俺様と撫子ちゃんは
一心同体のパートナーだと
思っていたが
D-Don't think that...
（千石）お… 思わないで
My words didn't sound convincing at all.
Animation Number 176
It's so hard to harshly tell someone off.
I was told to do something about the atmosphere of the classroom quite a while ago.
クラスの あの雰囲気を
なんとかしろって言われてるの
結構前から
Huh?
Come on, what's with that? Isn't that the job of the teacher in charge of that class?
おいおい なんだ そりゃ
それは担任の先生様の
お仕事じゃないのかい？
（千石）
うん まあ そのとおりなんだけどね
Yeah. Well, you're right about that.
You could say, it's tossing all responsibility to someone else.
いわゆる 丸投げってことだね
Ain't that even worse than me?
俺様よりひどいんじゃねえのか
そりゃ
Even after one glance, I can see that atmosphere isn't something one child can fix from the inside, huh?
チラッと見ただけでも
あんなもんが 一人の子供に
内側から解決できる
雰囲気じゃねえことは分かるぜ
ああん？
Serpent / speaking
Animation Number 114
It's all right.
（千石）別に いいんだよ
The matter is already behind me.
Animation Number 183
I'm not troubled by it or anything, so I'm fine.
別に撫子は
何も困ってないから 大丈夫
I've left it way behind me already.
Animation Number 184
Not troubled?
（クチナワ）困ってない？
I'm not troubled.
（千石）困ってない
You missed the mark.
Animation Number 186
Because I really have done nothing about it.
だって 別に撫子
何もしてないもの
Nothing?
（クチナワ）何も？
None of my work as class prez, and none of the work my teacher entrusted me with.
（千石）
委員長の仕事も
先生から頼まれた仕事も
The bell will ring soon.
Animation Number 187
I haven't done anything.
何もしてないもの
And so, I started to walk downstairs.
（千石）
と言って撫子は
階段を降り始めました
Kuchinawa-san became very silent. I wonder if he took the hint.
クチナワさんは静かになりました
空気を
読んでくれたのでしょうか？
After that bit, Kuchinawa-san didn't say a single word until school was out.
そのあと 放課後になるまで
クチナワさんは
ひと言もしゃべりませんでした
Animation Number 191
That night, just like I promised Kuchinawa-san, I went out looking for his corpse.
（千石）
その日の夜
撫子は
クチナワさんとの約束どおり
クチナワさんの死体探しに
出かけます
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I snuck out of the house.
（千石）
こっそりと家を出ます
Kuchinawa-san,
（千石）クチナワさん
How should I look for the vessel?
クチナワさんの神体を
撫子は
どういうふうに探せばいいの？
In the end, the vessel is my physical body.
（クチナワ）
神体ってのは
つまるところ俺様の肉体だから
So if I pass near it, I'll be vibrating like a cell phone on silent mode.
その近くを通れば
携帯電話のバイブみてえに
俺様が振動するんだ
So I just have to keep walking without stopping?
つまり 撫子は
このまま足を止めずに
歩いていればいいってこと？
Wh-What is it?
な… なに？
We already have a response!
おいおい 早速反応があったぜ
In the direction of 5 o'clock!
Animation Number 215
Wh-What? Are you saying your corpse is buried in this sandbox?
（千石）な… 何？
この砂場に クチナワさんの死体が
埋まっているって言うの？
No doubt about it.
（クチナワ）ああ 間違いないぜ
If you say so, Kuchinawa-san... I'll look here just in case.
クチナワさんが そう言うのなら
一応 探してはみるね
Animation Number 221
（千石）ハア〜 クチナワさん
Kuchinawa-san...
Hey, Kuchinawa-san.
ねえ クチナワさん
Hey, the vessel isn't here.
ねえ ないんだけど ご神体
Hey! Hey! Hey!
Animation Number 227
Now you're staying silent.
It's not here...
ないんだけど！
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Heh, it looks like that was a false alarm.
（クチナワ）
フフッ
どうやら誤作動だったようだな
F-False alarm?
ご… 誤作動って
I-If it's a false alarm, l-let me know a bit earlier!
ご… 誤作動なら誤作動で
もっと早く教えてよ
Why are there false alarms?
そもそも誤作動は
なんで起きるの？
Is it something like Doraemon's "Missing Person Cane" only having 70% accuracy?
ドラえもんの
“たずね人ステッキ”の的中率が
70パーセントみたいなもの？
No, it's not that.
（クチナワ）
いや そうじゃねえよ
That's quite an otaku way to put it.
Animation Number 233
Simply put, it just means that my spiritual energies have been dispersed.
俺様の霊的エネルギーが
散ってしまっているってことだ
単純にな
Dispersed?
（千石）散っている？
More like forcefully dispersed.
（クチナワ）
散らされていると言うべきかな
Then in any case, we can try again tomorrow...
じゃあ 何にせよ また明日だね
Serpent opposes
Animation Number 240
Come on now, Nadeko-chan, you quit too easily. What kind of genius gambler are you?
Serpent opposes
Animation Number 240
（クチナワ）
おいおい 撫子ちゃん
Serpent opposes
Animation Number 240
引き際が良すぎるな
どこの天才ギャンブラーだよ
Why not try one more spot instead of giving up so easily?
諦めずに もう１か所くらい
当たってみねえかい？
ダメ 疲れた
No go. I'm tired.
Your servant is very tired, master.
Animation Number 241
Since I went through so much effort, not only did I fill up the several holes I had dug,
（千石）
せっかくだからということで
掘ったいくつかの穴を
埋めるだけではなく
小さな山とかお城とかを作って
but I ended up playing by making things like small mountains and castles. That was wrong of me.
本当に遊んでしまったのが
いけませんでした
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Oh, I found you, Sengoku!
あっ 見つけた　千石！
K-Koyomi-oniichan?
こ… 暦おにいちゃん！
Koyomi-oniichan.
（千石）
暦おにいちゃん
Accidentally,
Animation Number 252
本名〝阿良々木暦〞
because I didn't hide well enough under my hat,
Animation Number 252
Full name: Araragi Koyomi.
our eyes met directly.
Animation Number 252
With a very serious look on his face...
シリアスな顔をして
Is he taking a stroll in the middle of the night?
夜中なのに散歩でしょうか？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 258
Listen up, Sengoku.
（阿良々木）いいか 千石
What you did was something anyone other than me would be completely furious about.
お前が やったことはな
相手が僕じゃなかったら
激怒されてるようなことなんだぜ
To leave your house late at night and be off fooling around somewhere...
夜中に家を抜け出て
フラフラと遊んでいるなんて
His little sisters' room
Animation Number 264
It seems that Koyomi-oniichan was looking for me.
（千石）
暦おにいちゃんは
撫子を捜していたそうです
Well, when my parents realized I had run away from home,
まあ その 撫子の家出に気付いた
お父さんとお母さんが
心当たりとしてかけた電話先が—
（着信音）
月火(つきひ)ちゃんだったのですね
they called Tsukihi-chan's place as somewhere I might likely be.
で 月火ちゃんは
月火ちゃんですから
And, Tsukihi-chan being Tsukihi-chan, thought "she'll be fine if it's one night"
“大丈夫だよ １晩ぐらい”
という感じで
and promptly replied with "she's over at our place" or a lie of that sort, but...
とっさに〝うちに
泊まっています〞なんて
You just happened by?
Koyomi-oniichan
Animation Number 271
ウソをついてくれた
らしいんですけれど…
バカ お前！
You idiot! What if Sengoku goes extinct because of that!
千石が絶滅したら どうするんだ！
And so he bolted out of the house and looked all over town for me.
（千石）
と家を飛び出し
町中を捜してくれていたそうです
In Koyomi's room
Animation Number 278
Really, if I hadn't found you, what would have happened to you by now?
まったく
僕が見つけていなければ
今頃どんなことになっていたか
I'm sorry.
（千石）ごめんなさい
（阿良々木）
いや まあ
反省してるならいいんだけどな
Well, if you're regretting what you did, that's fine.
Hmm?
Question
Animation Number 281
So, what is it?
Question
Animation Number 281
で 何だよ
Question
Animation Number 281
Why is a good kid like you walking around so late at night?
どうして こんな夜中に
お前みたいな いい子が
出歩いていたんだ？
I just...
Animation Number 282
It's not like in June.
ん？　千石 まさか お前
Sengoku, don't tell me...
Don't tell me that what you told me on the phone last night was a lie
まさか お前
ひょっとして昨日の夜
電話で言っていたのはウソで
and you've gotten involved in some difficult situation?
何か厄介事(やっかいごと)に
巻き込まれてるんじゃ…
I'm not a victim.
Animation Number 286
Th-That's not it.
I'm not a victim.
Animation Number 286
（千石）
ち… 違うよ
I'm not a victim.
Animation Number 286
Oh, okay, that's not it. I'm glad.
ああ そっか
違うんだ よかった
He actually believed it.
Animation Number 287
I totally thought that some aberration I'm not aware of smooth-talked you
てっきり僕は
千石が僕に隠れて
怪異にうまいこと言いくるめられて
and asked a favor of you to its advantage, like looking for something,
探しものだり何だり
何か都合のいい頼み事をされて
あの砂場を
掘り起こしていたのかと思ったぜ
and you dug up that sandbox looking for it.
Not at all... It's nothing like that.
全然 そんなことないよ
Spot on.
Animation Number 290
J-Just a bit... Well, my class has a lot of troubles right now, and I'm the class prez...
ちょ… ちょっと その…
今 クラスが
いろいろとトラブってて
撫子は委員長で
Some believable excuse.
Animation Number 291
Something that really is relevant nowadays.
だ… だから
なんだか しんどくなって
S-So things are just getting very tough on me, and I suddenly wanted to get out of the house.
ふいに
家を出たくなっちゃったんだよ
Oh, I see.
（阿良々木）ああ なるほどね
Things like that happen.
そういうことって あるよな
I understand how you feel, but Sengoku...
しかし
気持ちは分かるが 千石
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
If you keep running away, things won't ever get resolved.
そうやって逃げていても
物事ってのは解決しないんだぜ
（千石）逃げても… 解決しない
If I keep running, things won't get resolved.
If anything, you could've asked me for advice about your classroom troubles.
（阿良々木）なんだったら
僕に相談してくれれば
よかったんだよ
教室での そのトラブルってのも
何だ？
まさか貝木(かいき)のおまじない絡みか？
What's it about? Something to do with Kaiki's charms?
Nope...
（千石）違うよ
Sengoku. You're still in junior high.
千石 別に中学生なんだし
He tells me
Animation Number 300
with a serious face.
I'm sure you have lots of worries and troubles right now,
悩み事も困り事も
たらふく あるだろうが
一人で抱え込むことはねえんだぜ
but there's no need to carry the weight by yourself.
I'm not really one to be consulted with, but I can at least listen to what you have to say.
僕なんか そう
相談に乗るって柄でもねえけれど
それでも
話を聞いてやる程度のことは
できるんだから
Th-That's true.
（千石）そ… そうだね
From now on, if I have anything troubling me,
これからは
何か困ったことがあったら
抱え込まずに 暦おにいちゃんに
相談するようにするね
I won't carry the weight by myself, and I'll ask for your advice.
Yeah, please do that.
ああ そうしてくれ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
For now, you must be tired, so rest a bit.
とりあえず
今日は疲れてるだろうから休めよ
Rest?
休めって？
Wait here a minute.
ちょっと待ってろ
Where did he go?
Animation Number 307
H-Hey, Kuchinawa-san...
ね… ねえ クチナワさん
Are we okay? He hasn't caught on to us, right?
大丈夫かな？　バレてないよね？
Kuchinawa-san?
クチナワさん？
Then Koyomi-oniichan came back.
Animation Number 316
Sorry to make you wait.
（阿良々木）
お待たせ
Then Koyomi-oniichan came back.
Animation Number 316
Here you go.
はい これ
Pajamas. I borrowed them from Tsukihi-chan.
寝巻き
月火ちゃんから借りてきた
Huh?
You should stay the night. It's already pretty late.
今夜は泊まっていけよ
もう遅いし
He didn't beat around the bush. He told me straight and direct.
Animation Number 321
Wh-Which room should I be sleeping in?
ど… どこの部屋で
寝ればいいのかな？
（阿良々木）
え？　いや どこの部屋って
Well, which room?
僕んちも そんなに
部屋があるわけじゃないんだし
My house doesn't have that many rooms,  so you'll have to sleep in this room...
ここで寝てもらうしか
ないんだけど
I-In Koyomi-oniichan's room?
（千石）
こ… 暦おにいちゃんの部屋で
On his bed?
暦おにいちゃんのベッドで！
Well, yeah. Since you're probably tired, you can use my bed.
（阿良々木）
うん？　まあ そうだな
疲れてるだろうし
ベッド 使ってくれよ
Th-That's too much... Y-You should be sleeping on the bed, Koyomi-oniichan!
そ… そんな
ベ… ベッドは
暦おにいちゃんが使ってよ
ななな… 撫子なんて
I-I'm perfectly fine sleeping under the bed!
ベッドの下で十分だよ！
How did you come up with that idea? That's scary.
（阿良々木）
どういう発想なんだ？
怖いよ
There's no way I could sleep well here.
Animation Number 331
Just sleep on the bed.
ちゃんとベッドで寝ろ
女子中学生をベッドの下で
眠らせたなんて言ったら
If I were to say I let a junior high girl sleep under the bed, that would cause a huge problem.
大問題に発展してしまう
ファイヤーシスターズから
恐怖の制裁を受けてしまうぜ
The Fire Sisters would have the most horrifying of sanctions for me.
（千石）
で… でも
暦おにいちゃんを差し置いて
B-But, I can't shove you aside, Koyomi-oniichan, and sleep alone on the bed.
撫子 一人が
ベッドで寝たりできないよ
（阿良々木）ああ
Oh no, no, that's fine.
As if what he said was completely normal,
Animation Number 334
いやいや 大丈夫
he put on a smile.
Animation Number 334
Two people should fit on that bed perfectly fine.
そのベッドなら
２人くらい寝られるから
Animation Number 336
Vampire Punch!
（忍）吸血鬼パンチ！
ぐわ！
Whew. That was a close one.
フウ… 危ないところじゃった
He was this close to breaking a metropolitan area ordinance. Jeez.
もう少しで 都条例に
引っかかってしまう
ところじゃったわい
Now...
（忍）さてと
Our senses are linked, so my master's pain becomes my pain as well.
感覚がリンクしておるから
我があるじ様の痛みは
わしの痛みになってしまうのじゃが
But it seems if I knock him unconscious without an instant of pain, I don't have any problems.
苦痛を与える暇もなく
気絶させてしまえば
問題はないようじゃの
Are you all right, bangs-girl?
大丈夫かの？　前髪娘
Risky, risky. I'm glad I somehow made it in time.
剣呑(けんのん) 剣呑
どうにか間に合ってよかったわい
危うくその年で うぬは
子供を産むことになっておったぞ
You were just about to be raising a child at your age.
（千石）
そ… そこまでの事態だったの？
I-It was that serious a situation?
Well, looking at you like this, I can definitely see why he'd think that...
（忍）
まあ こうして見ると
確かに分からんでもないの
My master is very keen on you. A rather orderly model we have.
我があるじ様が
うぬに執心するのもな
かなり整った造形をしておる
ふむ
Her fangs sticking out between her lips
Animation Number 355
Second cutest after me!
わしの次にかわいい
Well, bangs-girl.
まあ 前髪娘よ
My master said this as well, but you should sleep on that bed tonight.
我があるじ様も言っておったが
今晩は
そのベッドで眠るがよかろう
I'll drag my master to the first floor and toss him on the sofa or something, so rest assured.
我があるじ様は
このまま１階に連れて降りて
ソファの上にでも
寝転がしておくから安心せい
Th...
It's just me...
Animation Number 360
I don't wanna cause a problem.
I'm sorry...
ごめんなさい
Hmph, you really apologize often.
フン！　よく謝る娘じゃのう
But what's the rationale?
じゃが どうなんじゃろうのう
うぬは悪いと思っておるから
謝っておるのか
Are you apologizing because you feel you're at fault
それとも ここは場面的に
謝るシチュエーションだから
or because you took the hint that "this is a situation where I should apologize" as if reading a script?
台本を読むように
空気を読んで謝っておるのか
Which is it, I wonder?
どちらなんじゃろうの？
Silence, huh?
だんまりか
Well, I'm not one to be able to comment on all of that.
まあ それについては
わしが何かを言える立場には
ないのう
I was quiet for quite a long time, just like that.
わしも随分 そうやって
黙り込んでいたものじゃしな
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
U-Um...
I couldn't resist asking.
Animation Number 372
（千石）
あ… あの…
Wh-What's so funny?
な… 何が おかしいんですか？
Funny? Hmph, there's nothing funny about this.
おかしい？
フフッ おかしいことなど ないわい
I merely laughed because I was just accepting the facts.
単に わしは
納得したから笑っただけじゃ
Merely by trembling like that, people lose the will to kill you.
そうやって ただただ
ブルブル震えておるだけで
殺す気がなくなってしまうような
うぬは 得でいいのう
I'm saying it must be nice to have that advantage.
という話じゃ
I-I don't have an advantage at all.
と… 得なんて… してないよ
Is that really so, huh?
本当にそうか？　んん？
Doubt
Animation Number 387
Just by staying quiet, aren't people nice to you?
黙っておるだけで
みんなが親切にしてくれたりは
せんのか？
Just by staying quiet, don't people think you're smart?
黙っておるだけで
頭がいいと思われたりせんのか？
Even if you fail, people don't get mad, right?
失敗しても
怒られたりせんのではないのか？
ウソをついても
許してもらえるのではないのか？
Even if you lie, don't people forgive you?
Th-That's...
（千石）そ… それが
Struggle to rebut
Animation Number 389
...that's exactly what I hate!
それが嫌なんだよ
That's not an advantage at all.
得じゃないよ そんなのは
Things like that are nothing but discrimination, and I-I...
そ… そんなのは
ただの差別みたいなもので
な… 撫子は…
She wouldn't listen
Animation Number 391
When you're in trouble...
（忍）
困っていると
...doesn't someone help you without asking?
誰かが勝手に助けてくれたりは
せんのかのう
もめていたら
勝手に被害者だと思ってくれたりの
Like if you were in a dispute, they assume that you were the victim...
ふむ
Hmph. I thought you might be playing the part on purpose, but it doesn't seem so.
ひょっとすると
わざと演じておるのかと
思っておったが
そういうわけでもないようじゃな
Which means you naturally act that way, with no special effort for that cuteness.
つまり 天然で
特に特別な努力はせず
そのかわいさで
そのしぐさか
"Naturally cute."
天然でかわいい
Do you know what they call beings like you in Japanese, by chance?
うぬのような存在を
ちなみに日本語では何と言うか
うぬは知っておるか？
Come now, that was a question. You can answer it.
おいおい 質問じゃぞ
答えていいんじゃぞ
I-I don't know. Fiendish?
わ… 分からないよ
きょ… 凶悪？
Fiendish
Animation Number 404
Devilish.
“魔性”じゃよ
I'm just saying, you're more of a monster than aberrations are.
うぬは怪異よりも
よっぽど妖怪じみておるという
話じゃよ
Scorn
Animation Number 409
No, no, it's all right. Sorry. I apologize. I spoke a bit too harsh.
いやいや いいんじゃよ
すまんすまん 言い過ぎたわい
Look down
Animation Number 410
人間ごときに
このわしともあろう者が
一体 何を言っておるのやら
What am I talking about to a mere human?
You can stay just the way you are.
うぬは そのままでよい
Keep living the way you do. I couldn't care less.
そのまま生きてろ
わしの知ったことではないわ
Live like that. And die like that.
そのまま生きて そのまま死ね
And like that, you can have Koyomi-oniichan worry about you for the rest of your life.
そうやって
一生 暦おにいちゃんに
心配してもらっておればよいわい
Good for you! That you just happened to be cute...
よかったな
たまたま かわいくて
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
（火憐(かれん)）火憐だぜ
（月火）月火だよ
Karen here!
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
（火憐･月火）
２人合わせて
ファイヤーシスターズ！
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
Decoy
（火憐）
予告編クイズ！
Preview Quiiiz!
Will everything be solved
if we find the holy grail?
（月火）
進行 巻きめだね
You seem earnest today.
（火憐）
囚人のジレンマって
知ってるか？
Do you know of the "Prisoner's Dilemma"?
（月火）
知ってる 知ってる
知り尽くしてる！
I know, I know, I know all about it!
（火憐）
最善の選択肢があるにも
関わらず
It's quite easy, psychologically speaking, to grasp why people always choose what's best for them.
人は心理的に それを
選べないという—
分かりやすい例なんだが
Let's find it for Nadeko-chan's sake!
しかし どうだろう
In that situation however, can some people really betray their partner?
心理的にっつうなら
実際 あの状況になって
仲間を裏切れる
ヤツなんかいるのかね
（月火）
う〜ん 正直 取り引きが
信用できないと思う
Honestly, I would find that kinda deal fishy anyway.
（火憐）
普通に交換条件を
出してくれればいいのに
Even if I was promised something in exchange,
Let's do our best tomorrow too, Fire Sisters!
You'd do that
for me? Thanks...
わざわざ仲間を
I would find hard to trust someone who thinks I could betray a partner.
裏切らせようとしている
ところが
信用ならねえぜ
（月火）
いっそ
こうすればいいのに
I'd rather go like this: "If you confess, your partner is free to go."
〝お前が自白すれば
相棒は解放してやる〞
案外 こっちのほうが
You're more likely to get a confession that way.
自白を
引き出せるのでは？
Listen Nadeko-chan!
You should give physical form
to your gratitude towards
the fire sisters
Right. I'll do that.
Wow!
（月火）
〝早く自白しないと〞
"Even if you don't confess, your partner will do it for your sake sooner or later anyway."
〝相棒がお前のために
自白するぞ〞
友情に訴えかける
作戦だよ
I call it the Friendship Gamble tactic!
（火憐）
しかし
不思議と残虐性は
Strangely, it feels even crueller than the regular approach.
増してる気がする
（火憐･月火）
次回「囮(おとり)物語」第３話
Next time! Otorimonogatari Episode 3!
Next Time
Nadeko Medusa Part 3
「なでこメドゥーサ
其ノ參(そのさん)」
Nadeko Medusa, Part 3.
（火憐）
撫子ちゃんと
何かあるんだって？
I heard there's something wrong with Nadeko-chan.
Lecturing
What did we do?
（月火）
黙秘します
I'm not telling anything.